Guide to the Dalkon Shield Claimants Trust Collection 1938-[1970-1998] 2000
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Many legal issues required judicial intervention during the course of the Trust's existence. One controversial issue concerned the Trust's holdback policy. In a case where a claimant was awarded a higher amount in litigation, the Trust reserved the right, upheld by the court, to defer paying the difference between the trial award and the original offer until there was assurance that all claims could be paid. Often when claimants brought their cases in state court, the Trust attempted to have them removed to federal court. There were many questions surrounding how ADR and arbitration would be handled. One case regarding burden of proof in ADR, Reichel v. Dalkon Shield Claimants Trust, was decided in the Trust's favor by the district court but partially overturned by the Fourth Circuit, which said that the claimant only had to provide a "presumption of causation." Plaintiffs were unsuccessful in getting this ruling to apply to arbitration and litigation.
In 1995 when the Trust began making pro rata payments, Judge Merhige on his own initiative issued an order limiting claimants' attorneys from recovering more that ten percent from those payments. One impetus for this ruling was complaints he had heard through the years from claimants whose attorneys had received a large percentage of their initial awards as contingent fees. The judge also knew that since pro rata payments would be made in cases that had been settled, little or no additional work was required of the attorneys. However, this order provoked protest from the plaintiffs' bar, and a group of twenty-nine lawyers appealed the order. The Fourth Circuit, calling "this litigation and appeal... wonderful examples of chutzpah," affirmed Judge Merhige's order.
Although Brown spent about ten years representing the Trust, and some of the cases stretched over many of those years, the legal costs were ultimately lower than anticipated. While a couple hundred cases were filed, in the end only about ninety went to trial. Nonetheless, the legal issues and claims that were litigated required the attention of the legal department for about five years after the vast majority of the claims were settled. Pro rata distributions from the remainder of the Trust were issued over time as the number of unresolved cases diminished.
VI. Conclusion The Disclosure Statement had given the Trust twenty years to settle 197,000 claims. With the allowance of late claims, the Trust ultimately paid a little over 218,000 claims and settled the vast majority of them in only seven years. Although the Trust operated particularly cautiously at the outset in order to be sure all claimants could be paid fairly, this extreme care worked to the benefit of the claimants in the end. Thanks in large part to the Trust's diligence, caution, and wise investments, the most seriously injured claimants saw their awards doubled. In terms of fairness and efficiency, the Dalkon Shield Claimants Trust achieved, in the opinion of many, the most successful resolution of a mass tort case in the twentieth century.
Scope and Content Information
The Dalkon Shield Claimants Trust Collection was transferred to the University of Virginia Law Library by an order of the U.S. Bankruptcy Court for the Eastern District of Virginia in September of 2000. Staff at the Trust first contacted the Law Library about the collection six months before the Trust was terminated at the end of April 2000. The collection came to the library in several installments between the late fall of that year and early 2001. It is comprised of 408 boxes and cartons of documents, 3 volumes, 416 three-ring notebooks, 271 videotapes, for a total of 327.5 linear feet; 139 reels of microfilm, and approximately 7500 pieces of microfiche, or approximately 170,000 items.
The Trust collection traces the history of the Dalkon Shield, the intrauterine contraceptive device manufactured and sold by the A.H. Robins Company, from the company's purchase of the device through its tort litigation and subsequent bankruptcy which was resolved in 1988. The collection also documents the establishment and history of the Dalkon Shield Claimants Trust, 1988-2000, which settled over 218,000 claims.
The collection is arranged in six series. Series I, the A.H. Robins (AHR) Company Documents, consist of company records which trace the purchase, manufacture, testing, marketing, and sale of the Dalkon Shield. Series II is comprised of AHR Litigation Documents, principally employee depositions and trial testimony. Series III concerns the U.S. Food and Drug Administration investigation of the Dalkon Shield, and Series IV, news articles regarding the Shield. Series V is comprised of bankruptcy materials, and Series VI consists of the administrative files of the Dalkon Shield Claimants Trust.
Contents List
- Series I: A.H. Robins Company Documents
  In 1975 a Multi-District Litigation Panel was set up to consolidate over one hundred Dalkon Shield personal injury tort cases pending in federal district courts in over a third of the states. The pretrial proceedings were held before U. S. District Judge Frank Theis in Wichita, Kansas. Bradley Post, a Wichita lawyer who had represented Connie Deemer, the first woman to win a verdict against Robins for her Dalkon Shield injuries, was chosen lead lawyer in the consolidated cases. Post led the court-ordered discovery proceedings that ran from 1976 through the late 1970s and resumed in 1981 and 1982.
  AHR was ordered to produce copies of tens of thousands of documents and to store them at the Richmond offices of McGuire, Woods & Battle, the law firm handling its defense. The collection of documents became known as the Source Files. Documents in the following subject categories were requested, copied and numbered at various times from 1976 through 1982: Research & Development, Adverse Reaction, Manufacturing, Administration, Commercial, Government, International, FDA (Food and Drug Administration), and Bibliography.
  In 1991, by administrative order, the Trust was directed to "maintain a document depository in Richmond, Virginia, containing substantially all documents which the Trust, using its best efforts, has identified as having been produced without qualification by Robins in pre-petition Dalkon Shield personal injury tort litigation." The depository, to be made accessible to claimants and their attorneys, was comprised of documents previously in the custody of McGuire, Woods and was located at Datastor, a facility on the east end of the city.
  The A.H. Robins Company documents consist of the master group, the Source Files, produced under the direction of Judge Frank Theis in the late 1970s and early 1980s. In addition, there are a number of subsets of the Source Files gathered and arranged by plaintiffs' attorneys, and additional documents produced under orders from other judges in the mid-1980s.
  - Series I Sub-series 1: AHR Source Files
    According to a Trust memorandum, (see notebook labeled Background Information re Document Depository), AHR and its attorneys began collecting, reviewing, and copying these documents, later known as the Source Files, as early as 1975. In 1976 when the Multi-District Litigation Panel was set up, the range of documents was expanded to include information on Robins' international sales, and on its interactions with Hugh Davis, Robert Cohn, Thad Earl, and Irwin S. Lerner. Plaintiffs involved in the MDL proceedings were allowed access to all documents that were not privileged. The copies, held in Richmond in the custody of McGuire, Woods, were made from the original documents.
    The Law Library completed a project begun sometime ago to convert the Source Files to microform. Documents 1 through 171, 245 are available on microfiche; and 171,246 through 211, 892, on microfilm. Researchers may gain access to the Source File documents through any of its four indexes: document number, document date, name of document writer, and document type and date. The indexes are in three-ring notebooks, and on microfilm reels 1 to 6.
    Two types of materials in the Source Files, numbers 189,673 through 207,502, are not in microform (4 cartons, 5 linear feet). The first are computer printouts of names and addresses of the 200,000 doctors to whom AHR wrote in the early 1980s, requesting removal of the Shield. Box 1 contains names and addresses for physicians in Colombia, Sweden, The Netherlands, South Africa, and Australia; Box 2, for Mexico, Philippines, Germany, Denmark, Finland, France, and Venezuela; and Box 3, for the United States. Second, in Box 4, is a collection of used Dalkon Shields sent back to AHR by Thad Earl, David Ostergard, and other doctors.
  - Series 1 Sub-series 2: Source File Subsets
    - Sub-sub-series 1: MDL Chronological ("Chrono") subset of the Source Files
      The MDL Chrono Files are a chronological arrangement of 1300 of some of the more important documents from the Source Files and were offered in evidence during the1976-1978 MDL discovery proceedings. The date range of the Chrono Files is 1938 to 1977, with the bulk of the documents falling between 1971 and 1975. In some cases the copy in the Chrono Files is more legible than the one in the Source Files.
      There is no list or index for the Chrono Files. Boxed with the files was a subject index to the first 183,000 SF documents; this index which pairs Source File number with subject was prepared in 1979. The Chrono Files are available on microfilm reels 19-22, as well as on paper in Boxes 1-6 (2.5 linear feet).
    - Sub-sub-series 2: Bradley Post's Selected Subset of the Source Files
      Bradley Post preserved a set of selected Robins Source File documents which he had submitted as evidence in a case around 1979. The Post documents are arranged chronologically and numbered 1 to 836 in the upper left corner; the Source File number is visible in the lower left corner. The date range is 1938 to 1979, with bulk dates of 1971 to 1975. The Post documents are available on microfilm reels 22 and 23. A list of numbered Post documents providing extensive information about each entry is available on paper and also precedes the documents on the film.
    - Sub-sub-series 3: Robins, Zelle Selected Subset of the Source Files
      In 1983 Robins, Zelle, Larson & Kaplan, a large firm in Minneapolis acquired about two hundred Dalkon Shield cases from another practice, and the firm appointed experienced plaintiffs' attorneys Dale Larson and Michael Ciresi to handle them. For the case of Shirley Dean v. A. H. Robins, the lawyers submitted as evidence 3,789 documents they had chosen from the Robins Source Files. Those documents comprise this subset and are arranged chronologically and numbered 1 to 3,789, usually near the top of the first page of the document; the Source File number is visible in the lower left corner. The dates range from 1938 to 1984, but are concentrated in the years 1970 to 1980. The Robins, Zelle documents are available on microfilm reels 23-31. The list of numbered Robins, Zelle documents provides extensive information about each entry; it is available on paper, and it also precedes the documents on the film.
  - Series I Sub-series 3: Judge Miles Lord Responsive, An Addition to the Source Files.
    In 1983 Minnesota U.S. District Judge Miles Lord began hearing Dalkon Shield cases. By early 1984 he believed there were pertinent documents AHR had not produced during multi-district proceedings in the late 1970s and early 1980s. He, therefore, ordered a re-opening of discovery specifically for a number of categories, including correspondence with Aetna, AHR's insurance company, correspondence between certain top company officials and AHR lawyers, and documents relating to testing of Dalkon Shield safety. Furthermore, Lord appointed two attorneys to go to Richmond to supervise the production of these documents.
    The Lord Responsive documents are available on microfilm reels 31-33. These document numbers appear at the end of the Source File Document Number Index, but since a substantial number of them did not pertain to Lord's order, or were privileged, there are not corresponding documents for all the numbers. An annotated copy of the Lord pages from the Index precedes the documents on the film, and there the researcher can determine which documents will appear.
  - Series I Sub-series 4: Zelius Production, An Addition to the Source Files
    In 1984 and early 1985 lawyers for Claire Zelius were preparing their case against AHR in Florida. The federal district court allowed them to seek additional Robins documents, principally unpublished scientific or medical studies on the Dalkon Shield tail string.
    The Zelius Production documents are available on microfilm reels 34-41. The documents have been numbered, although there is no corresponding index for them in the Source Files index. Available on paper, and preceding the Zelius documents on microfilm, is an index which ties production date to a note book number, followed by another index which is a short list of doctors' names for depositions they gave in other cases.
  - Series I Sub-series 5: Dalkon Shields
    Production commenced on the Dalkon Shield intrauterine device in 1968 under the direction of inventors Hugh Davis, gynecologist, and Irwin Lerner, electrical engineer. In early 1970 Davis and Lerner looked for a pharmaceutical company to market their product more widely, and by June of that year, AHR agreed to purchase it.
    The Dalkon Shield came in two sizes: standard, for women who had already had children (multiparous), and small, for women who had never had children (nulliparous). Shaped somewhat like a law enforcement officer's badge, hence its name, the Shield had five fingers protruding along each side, so that it also looked somewhat like a crab. Tied to its base was a three-inch length of synthetic polyfilament otherwise used for surgical sutures. In the case of the Shield, this filament, called the tail string, was principally designed for easy removal of the IUD.
    The A.H. Robins Company began production and sales in early 1971. Domestic sales were suspended in June of 1974, although foreign sales continued until August 1975. By the time sales ceased altogether, 3,600,000 Dalkon Shields had been sold worldwide.
    This sub-series of 7 boxes (2.9 linear feet) consists of packets of standard and small Dalkon Shields produced by the Dalkon Corporation and by A.H. Robins Co. In addition there are examples of boxes in which the packets were distributed; instruction sheets for physicians and patients; publicity material; rolls of the tail string material, loose shields, and various instruments. Finally, there is a videotape made by the Dalkon Corporation to demonstrate insertion and placement of the Dalkon Shield.
    - Two packets of standard Shields with production number 6030; manufactured by the Dalkon Corporation, Stamford, CT 1970 (Box 1)
    - One packet of standard Shields without a production number; manufactured for A.H. Robins Co., Richmond, VA July 1970 (Box 1)
    - Nine packets of standard Shields numbered A7041, A7141, & A7201; manufactured for AHR April 1971 (Box 1)
    - Six packets of standard Shields numbered A7381, A7511, 715711, and not numbered; manufactured for AHR July 1971 (Box 1)
    - Seven packets of standard Shields numbered 72239 & 72329; manufactured for AHR June 1972 (Box 1)
    - Nineteen packets of standard Shields numbered 73424, 73978, 731129, & 7312210; manufactured for AHR December 1972 (Box 2)
    - Fourteen packets of standard Shields numbered 73263 & 73282; manufactured for AHR; bearing label Property of the Mexican Institute of Social Security.../Patent Number 113,969/November 12, 1969 December 1972 (Box 3)
    - Box for packets of standard Shields numbered F030; manufactured by the Dalkon Corporation, Stamford, CT 1970 (Box 3)
    - Box of standard Shields bearing no production number; manufactured for A.H. Robins Co., Richmond, VA July 1970 (Box 3)
    - Box for packets of standard Shields numbered 715711; manufactured for the A.H. Robins Co., Richmond, VA April 1971 (Box 3)
    - Box for packets of standard Shields numbered 73424; manufactured for AHR June 1972 (Box 3)
    - Two packets of small Shields with production number 6200; manufactured by the Dalkon Corporation, Stamford, CT 1970 (Box 4)
    - Ten packets of small Shields numbered 6430, 6450, 645016 & n.d.; manufactured for A.H. Robins Co., Richmond, VA 1970 (Box 4)
    - One packet of small Shields numbered A6931; manufactured for AHR November 1970 (Box 4)
    - Seventeen packets of small Shields numbered A7091, A7341, 71359, 71369, & 71379; manufactured for AHR April 1971 (Box 4)
    - Twelve packets of small Shields numbered A7351, A7471, & 72196; manufactured for AHR July 1971 (Box 5)
    - Thirty-two packets of small Shields numbered 72308, 72329, 73131, 73313, 725711, & 726812; manufactured for AHR June 1972 (Box 5)
    - Fifteen packets of small Shields numbered 73696 & 74615; manufactured for AHR December 1972 (Box 6)
    - Box for small Shields bearing production number 6200; manufactured for AHR July 1970 (Box 6)
    - Box for small Shields packets numbered 71369; manufactured for AHR April 1971 (Box 6)
    - Box for small Shield packets numbered 73696; manufactured for AHR June 1972 (Box 6)
    - Brochures about the Dalkon Shield November 1970, March 1971 (Box 7)
    - Instructions for Physician and Patient July 1972, August 1972 & January 1973 (Box 7)
    - "Cold Sterilization" Procedures...; instructions in English, French and Spanish n.d. (Box 7)
    - Brochure about Dalkon Contraceptive Foam March 1973 (Box 7)
    - General Instructions for Physicians in English, French, and Spanish May 1973 (Box 7)
    - Supramid Extra, Size 0; 2 rolls white and 8 rolls black; "Synthetic, polyamide, non-absorbable, polyfilament, Class II, surgical suture." (Box 7)
    - Inserter Sticks, 8 (Box 7)
    - [Foam models for insertion practice?], 4 (Box 7)
    - Two bags of loose multiparous shields (Box 7)
    - Two medical instruments probably used for Dalkon Shield removal (Box 7)
    - Dalkon Shield Insertion film prepared by the Dalkon Corporation n.d., V1-Video 1
  - Sub-series 6: Miscellaneous AHR Documents Providing an Overview of the Company and Dalkon Shield Production and Sales
    - (First Quarter) AHR Annual Reports 1966-1985, 20 folders (Box 1)
    - AHR Press Releases 1970-1984 (Box 2)
    - Dalkon Shield packaging information and patient information n.d. (Box 2)
    - Packaging Information--other IUDs n.d. (Box 2)
    - Pre-January 1971 Testing of Dalkon Shield 1970, 1974 (Box 2)
    - AHR Dalkon Shield purchase documents 1970 (Box 2)
    - Dalkon Shield trademark 1971 (Box 2)
    - Inserter stick--patents, etc 1971 (Box 2)
    - Dalkon Shield Manufacturing and Quality Assurance Manual 1973 (Box 2)
    - Foreign distribution of Dalkon Shield 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - "Dear Doctor" letters-domestic 1974 (Box 2)
    - Glossary of individuals relevant to Dalkon Shield n.d. (Box 2)
  - Series I Sub-series 6: Miscellaneous AHR documents providing an overview of the company and Dalkon Shield production and sales
    This two-box collection (0.8 linear feet) of miscellaneous A. H. Robins Company documents, assembled by the Trust, provides a bird's eye view of the purchase, production, and sale of the Dalkon Shield from 1970 to 1985. All of these documents can be located in the Source Files, but researchers may find these two boxes provide a convenient, simple and accessible introduction to the history of Robins and the Shield.
- Series II: A.H. Robins Litigation Documents
  During the multi-district litigation proceedings from the late 1970s through the early 1980s, many employees of AHR were deposed, and their depositions made accessible to plaintiffs' lawyers all over the country. When the Trust set up the document depository for the use of claimants, the MDL depositions were included. In addition, depositions not under the aegis of the MDL panel, as well as a great deal of trial testimony of A. H. Robins employees, became part of the document depository. The Trust legal department also had a core collection of depositions, exhibits, etc. for their own attorneys' use in litigation. Materials in this series are principally on microfilm or videotape.
  - Sub-series 1: AHR Employee Depositions and Testimony
    - Sub-sub-series 1: MDL Depositions
      In 1976 when Bradley Post, on behalf of plaintiffs' attorneys, was seeking Robins documents for multi-district litigation, dozens of top officials in the A. H. Robins Co. were being deposed. The following Robins employees were deponents: Ernest L. Bender, Jr., Dr. John I. Brewer, John Leo Burke, Dr. A.N. Chremos, Dr. Fred A. Clark, Jr., Robert E. Cohn, Elderin Wayne Crowder, Dr. Hugh J. Davis, Dr. Roy William Dent, Thomas D. Downs, Dr. Thad J. Earl, Dorothy Kimball Ervin, William A. Forrest, Jr., Daniel Eugene French, Jack Freund, Edwin Hood, A.J. Kapadia, Oscar Klioze, Irwin Lerner, Frank William Mann, A. Edwin Martin, David Mefford, Kenneth Moore, C.E. Morton, Dr. Robert S. Murphey, Dr. Fletcher B. Owen, Jr., Allen Polon, Dr. Ellen Preston, Dr. Lester W. Preston, E.C. Robins, Melvin Rohling, W. Roy Smith, Ritchie Alan Snyder, Robert Walker Tankersley, Howard James Tatum, Dale Taylor, George E. Thomas, Roger Lewis Tuttle, Richard A. Velz, John Wesley Ward, Thomas C. Yu, and William L. Zimmer III.
      Depositions were taken from 1976 through 1983. These transcripts, available on microfilm reels 42-55, are arranged alphabetically by deponent and then chronologically. Most depositions lasted from one to four consecutive days, although a few deponents were called back for a second time. Some depositions are followed by exhibits, summaries, and/or objections. An index precedes the documents on the microfilm.
    - Sub-sub-series 2: Non-MDL Depositions
      At the same time of the MDL discovery process, Robins officials were being deposed for cases not included in the multi-district litigation. The following Robins employees were deponents: Jerald Eugene Adams, Frank Bedrick, Ernest L. Bender, Jr., Dr. Anne J. W. Board, Eleanor Bradley, Bob L. Brown, Jeneal D. Brummett, John Leo Burke, John S. Campana, Edward C. Casey, Robert F. Childs, Dr. A.N. Chremos, Charles F. Christopher, Eugenia Clark, Dr. Fred A. Clark, Jr., Ben Clarkson, Robert E. Cohn, Everett L. Cook, Thomas E. Costa, Carlyne Crotty, Elderin Wayne Crowder, Arthur R. Cummings, Darwin Carl Dahl, Dr. Hugh J. Davis, Charles T. Degolia, Dr. Roy William Dent, Jr., Erich De Romero, Calvin R. De Witt, Charles S. Donahue, Paul M. Duffy, Jr., Hartwell Durrance, Thomas D. Downs, Dr. Thad Joseph Earl, John A. Emerick, Dorothy Kimball Ervin, Jeanne Featherston, William A. Forrest, Jr., Daniel Eugene French, Dr. Jack Freund, Anne Friedman, John E. Gallapago, John T. Gaywood, Michael Gibb, Frank W. Gilbert, Donald Thomas Gillooly, Robert L. Gorvett, Lawrence Griffin, John Vincent Guiney, Ray Hanchey, William D. Hart, Jr., Norval Haugh, Dennis F. Heikka, Dr. E.B. Heilman, Doral Loren Hessman, Douglas Arthur Hewey, Robert A. Hogsett, Thomas B. Horne, Robert F. Hunley, David E. Jones, Herbert Joyce, Jr., Duwaine F. Kaufman, James W. Kennedy, Sidney M. Kessler, Louis Kilgore, Daniel Klimpel II, Oscar Klioze, David Mayer Koepke, John P. Kypriotis, Leonard Clayton Lacy, John P. Lage, Raymond L. Langston, Patricia Lashley, Irwin S. Lerner, Charles Hunter Leys, George Lobeck, Gene Ross Lucas, and Carl D. Lunsford.